Is it possible that this monkey demon
难道这猴魔
is the murderer?
是凶手吗？
He's good
他很好
in agility.
在敏捷性方面。
What if the monkey demon
如果是猴妖怎么办
is just a smokescreen released by the murderer
只是 凶手释放的烟幕弹
and the murderer's target
以及凶手的目标
is not the two people you both are watching?
不是 你们两个都在看的两个人吗？
Well,
出色地，
you are alone.
你孤身一人。
Not only me.
不只是我。
We have all split up.
我们都已经分手了。
All alone.
独自一人。
And also,
并且，
we don't know where the murderer is,
我们不知道凶手在哪里
yet the murderer knows exactly where each of us is.
但凶手却 清楚地知道我们每个人在哪里。
We aren't concerned about the monkey demon.
我们不关心 猴妖。
My senior and I will protect you.
我和我的前辈会保护你的。
In this way,
这样，
the murderer will be bold
凶手一定会胆大妄为
to kill the two people you are watching.
杀死你正在观看的两个人。
This adversary of ours
我们的这个对手
is not simple.
并不简单。
However, when I think about it,
然而，当我想到这一点时，
these two people
这两个人
sort of deserve to die.
有点该死。
=Ripe Town= =Episode 7=
=成熟小镇= =第7集=
Take this back.
把这个收回来。
You win this bet.
你赢了这个赌注。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Don't thank me.
别谢我。
Well,
出色地，
you can thank this monkey demon.
你可以感谢这个猴妖。
Has Captain Xia already taken him back to the Nietai Yamen?
夏队长已经带他 回聂台衙门了吗？
He just left.
他刚刚离开。
He got an interrogation record?
他有审讯笔录吗？
I already had one.
我已经有一个了。
But after Captain Xia returns to the Nietai Yamen,
但夏队长回到 聂台衙门后，
surely he will use some torture
他肯定会使用一些酷刑
to get something useful for him.
去得到一些对他有用的东西。
He will pin this case on the monkey demon.
他会把这件案子 归咎于猴妖。
If Captain Xia intends to falsely accuse someone,
如果夏队长有意 诬告某人，
it's hard to think of a perfect confession.
很难想象 有什么完美的表白。
A captain and a teacher were killed.
一名队长和一名老师被杀。
It's difficult to fabricate the motive.
很难捏造动机。
So it is you.
所以是你。
What do you mean?
你是什​​么意思？
It's something common in the Yamen.
这在衙门里是常有的事。
The confiscated items often contain some extra stuff
没收的物品 通常含有一些额外的东西
that happens to be useful for the bailiff in their case-solving.
这恰好对法警破案有用。
Captain Leng's badge was among them.
冷队长的徽章就在其中。
You put it in.
你把它放进去。
Mr. Song.
宋先生。
I bet you have never visited
我打赌你从来没有去过
the watchhouse of the Hunter Squad.
猎人小队的岗哨。
After we
之后我们
hand over shifts,
交班，
we will hang our badges on the wall.
我们会将徽章挂在墙上。
(Although my master is gone,)
（虽然我的师父已经不在了，）
(I still keep his badge)
（我还保留着他的徽章）
(in the watchhouse.)
（在看守所里。）
(I wipe it every day.)
（我每天都会擦。）
(Probably,)
（大概，）
(they noticed it.)
（他们注意到了。）
You want to use that thief
你想利用那个小偷
to send away Captain Xia.
送走夏队长。
That thief is not wronged.
那个小偷并没有受委屈。
I will find the real culprit.
我会找到真正的罪魁祸首。
By then, I'll just sentence that thief
到时候我就判那个小偷
for theft.
盗窃。
Check it out.
一探究竟。
This is a list of antiques purchased.
这是购买的古董清单。
It's found among the stolen goods of that monkey demon.
这是在那个猴妖的赃物中发现的。
Captain Xia thought it was useless.
夏队长觉得没什么用。
It's another common practice in the Yamen.
这也是 衙门里的一种常见做法。
Misleading things
误导性的事情
will disappear from the evidence.
将从证据中消失。
It looks like a note by an antique dealer.
它看起来像是古董商的便条。
It's the kind who goes from house to house collecting antiques.
就是挨家挨户收集古董的那种。
It notes what he collected from which family
它记录了他 从哪个家庭收集的东西
and how much money he spent.
以及他花了多少钱。
The monkey demon committed crimes
猴妖犯下罪行
according to this list.
根据这个列表。
He's smart, right?
他很聪明，对吧？
The people who just sold an antique
刚刚卖掉古董的人
are bound to have money.
一定有钱。
Where did this monkey demon get this list?
这猴妖是从哪里 得到这份名单的？
From the Mao County.
茂县人。
There's a place called Taipingzao.
有一个地方，叫太平灶。
It's a den of thieves disposing of stolen goods.
这是小偷处理赃物的窝点。
It's not unusual for antique dealers
对于古董商来说这并不罕见
to buy stolen goods at the Taipingzao.
去太平灶买赃物。
It's also quite common to sell the purchasing list to thieves.
将采购清单出售给窃贼的情况也很常见。
I have already sent people to get their leader.
我已经派人 去找他们的首领了。
But most likely, they won't be able to get him.
但最有可能的是， 他们无法得到他。
Mr. Song.
宋先生。
I still think there's nothing suspicious about this.
我仍然认为 这没有什么可疑之处。
It's nothing suspicious?
没什么可疑的吧？
I have asked the owners
我已经问过业主了
of lost properties.
丢失的财产。
They all said that they had no antiques.
他们都说自己没有古董。
What?
什么？
Or they don't consider these goods
或者他们不考虑这些商品
as antiques.
作为古董。
The antique dealer came to them,
古董商来到他们面前，
insisting that their broken bowls,
坚持认为他们的破碗，
old pots, and old fans were antiques.
旧壶、旧扇都是古董。
He paid a lot of money to buy them.
他花了很多钱买它们。
He sold the list to the monkey demon through the Taipingzao.
他通过太平灶将名单卖给了猴妖。
That's to say,
也就是说，
he lured the monkey demon here.
他把猴妖引到了这里。
And he made the monkey demon appear
他让猴妖出现了
as planned.
正如计划。
But why did he do that?
但他为什么要这么做呢？
According to the victims,
据受害者称，
this antique dealer
这位古董商
is a bearded man in a bamboo hat.
是一个戴着斗笠、长着胡须的男子。
Poor monkey demon.
可怜的猴魔。
Captain Xia wants to use him.
夏队长想要利用他。
You want to use him.
你想利用他。
Even the murderer wants to use him.
就连凶手也想利用他。
He probably
他大概
has never been so useful in his life.
他一生中从未如此有用过。
(Yaowang Temple)
(Yaowang Temple)
(Such a person could actually get such a disease.)
（这样的人 其实也可能得这种病。）
Another one died.
另一人死了。
Dr. Cheng Yizhi.
Dr. Cheng Yizhi.
He felt my pulse the other day.
那天他给我摸了脉搏。
A bailiff,
一名法警，
a teacher,
一位老师，
and a doctor.
和一名医生。
What on earth does the murderer want?
凶手到底想要什么？
Sir.
先生。
We can first investigate
我们可以先调查一下
the cause of death of Dr. Cheng.
郑医生的死因。
Yes.
是的。
Coroner.
验尸官。
What's the cause of death?
死因是什么？
Sir.
先生。
Dr. Cheng's face was purple,
程医生脸色紫了，
and his lips black.
他的嘴唇是黑色的。
I determined that he was poisoned.
我断定他是中毒了。
What poison?
什么毒？
I don't know.
我不知道。
Sir, may I say something?
先生，我可以说句话吗？
Who's he?
他是谁？
This is Mr. Liu, the owner of Bao'an Pharmacy.
这是宝安大药房老板刘先生。
We found dozens of prescriptions
我们找到了几十个处方
on the body,
在身体上，
and the large pot where the body was placed
以及放置尸体的大锅
was full of medical residues.
充满了医疗残留物。
So he was specially invited to help.
于是特意请他来帮忙。
mr. Liu.
先生。刘.
Yes.
是的。
What do you want to say?
你想说什么？
Sir.
先生。
The prescriptions have Mr. Cheng's seal.
处方上有程先生的印章。
And these residues are from the medicine on the prescriptions.
而这些残留物就是 处方上的药物。
In my opinion, Mr. Cheng was poisoned by the medicine
我认为 程先生是中药中毒了
he prescribed.
他开了处方。
Poison?
毒？
How could Dr. Cheng
程医生怎么可以
prescribe himself poisonous medicine?
给自己开毒药？
No.
不。
Mr. Cheng's prescriptions have no issues.
程先生的处方 没有问题。
They're for the treatment of ordinary diseases.
它们用于治疗 普通疾病。
But different herbs have different doses.
但不同的草药 有不同的剂量。
It seems
它似乎
that the murderer brewed the medicines
凶手酿造了药物
from dozens of prescriptions
从数十张处方中
and then fed them to Mr. Cheng.
然后喂给程先生。
The medicines are not poisonous,
药物没有毒，
but they become poisonous when mixed.
但它们混合后会有毒。
All herbs contain trace amounts of poison.
所有草药都含有微量 的毒。
There are medicinal ingredients like Kusnezoff Monkshood,
有 草附子等药用成分，
henbane, and windflower in these prescriptions.
这些处方中的天仙子、白头翁花 。
It's surely lethal at such a dosage.
这样的剂量肯定是致命的。
Such a person could actually get such a disease.
这样的人， 居然会得这样的病。
I've looked into it.
我已经调查过了。
As Ran Boniu, a disciple of Confucius,
正如孔子的弟子冉伯牛所说，
fell seriously ill,
患了重病，
Confucius said that.
孔子如是说。
It just means such a person
就是指这样一个人
could actually get such a disease.
居然会得这样的病。
A doctor could actually be killed by his own medicine.
医生实际上可能会 被自己的药杀死。
That's why the murderer
这就是凶手的原因
left this note.
留下了这张纸条。
Mr. Xie.
Mr. Xie.
Shall we report this case?
我们要举报这个案子吗？
Yes.
是的。
I've drafted the document.
我已经起草了文件。
Please review it.
请查看。
Good.
好的。
Let's go.
我们走吧。
Captain Xia.
Captain Xia.
He only knows how to flog people and catch monkeys.
他只知道打人 、抓猴子。
I must file a complaint against him.
我必须对他提出投诉。
Mr. Song.
宋先生。
I'll take my leave.
我先告辞了
Please wait.
请稍等。
mr. Liu.
先生。刘.
Please check the two prescriptions.
请检查这两个处方。
By Dr. Cheng.
程博士撰文。
Prescribed 20 years ago.
20年前规定的。
As you said,
如你所说，
if the medicines from the two prescriptions
如果两个处方中的药物
are administered to one patient,
给予一名患者，
what will happen?
会发生什么？
Qu Sangeng.
Qu Sangeng.
Where did you
你在哪
get the prescriptions?
拿到处方了吗？
They were left by my master.
它们是我的主人留下的。
I'm not sure if they're related to this case.
我不确定 他们是否与本案有关。
So...
所以...
Sir.
先生。
mr. Liu.
先生。刘.
What do you think?
你怎么认为？
Suppose you mix the medicines
假设你混合药物
from these two prescriptions together,
从这两个处方一起来看，
it's okay
没关系
to let Chen Wang eat it.
让陈王吃掉。
But if it is given to this Lu Yuanbao,
但如果给这个陆元宝的话，
it will be lethal for him.
这对他来说是致命的。
What will happen to him?
他会发生什么事？
Within half a year,
半年之内，
he will start vomiting blood.
他会开始吐血。
If he continues to take the medicine, his life will be at serious risk.
如果他继续服药， 他的生命将面临严重危险。
mr. Liu.
先生。刘.
I remember that anyone who buys herbs in the pharmacy
我记得凡是 在药房买草药的人
must leave a copy of their prescription.
必须留下一份处方副本。
Yes.
是的。
This is to make sure there's a clear record
这是为了确保 有清晰的记录
in case the patient has any problem.
如果患者有任何问题。
So, even if the patient dies, they can check
所以，即使病人死亡， 他们也可以检查
the prescription in the pharmacy.
药房的处方。
Dr. Cheng won't be to blame.
程医生不会受到责备。
Yes.
是的。
Coroner.
验尸官。
If a person dies from that, and you are to perform the autopsy,
如果一个人因此而死亡， 而你要进行尸检，
will you see it as death by poisoning?
你会认为这是中毒死亡吗？
No.
不。
My condition has been erratic for the past six months.
过去六个月我的病情一直不稳定。
My days are limited.
我的日子有限。
You don't need to worry.
你不用担心。
In my opinion, you look fine now.
在我看来，你现在看起来很好。
You only need time for recuperation and rest.
你只需要时间 恢复和休息。
Thank you, Dr. Cheng.
谢谢郑博士。
Please have a good rest.
请好好休息。
I'll take my leave.
我先告辞了
(Dr. Cheng's medical skills came from his family.)
（程医生的医术来自 于他的家庭。）
(But there's one skill that no one knows)
（但是有一项技能 没人知道）
(where he learned it.)
（他在那里学到的。）
Mr. Cheng.
Mr. Cheng.
Let Mr. Lu take the first dose around five p.m.
下午五点左右让陆先生服用第一剂
Yes, I see.
好的我知道了。
But before taking this first dose,
但在服用第一剂之前，
he needs to take the Chongxu Powder.
他需要服用冲虚散。
It needs to be brewed with boiling water.
需要用 沸水冲泡。
And leave it for four hours.
并放置四个小时。
Now is the time to do it.
现在是时候这样做了。
Go quickly to the kitchen to brew it.
赶紧去厨房煮。
Sir, I will do it after I walk you out.
先生，我送您出去后就会做。
You don't have to. The patient can't wait.
你不必这样做。 病人等不及了。
You should go right now.
你应该现在就走。
I'm leaving.
我走了。
Go ahead.
前进。
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
Dr. Cheng
Dr. Cheng
stole again when he came for the follow-up visit.
当他来复诊时又偷了。
(What did he steal?)
（他偷了什么？）
He stole
他偷了
a sandalwood canister carved with a golden toad.
刻有金蟾蜍的檀香罐。
(Since you knew he was stealing,)
（既然你知道他在偷东西，）
(why didn't you catch him?)
（你为什么不抓住他？）
We invited him to treat Mr. Lu.
我们请他给卢先生看病。
He is the best doctor in our county.
他是我们县最好的医生。
Catching him would do us no good.
抓住他对我们没有好处。
But I've hidden all the important things
但我隐藏了所有重要的事情
and left inexpensive items for him to steal.
并留下便宜的物品 让他偷。
I'll consider it as his fee.
我会把它当作他的费用。
However,
然而，
I recorded all the things he stole.
他偷走的东西我都记录下来了。
(What is this?)
（这是什么？）
An ink stick.
一根墨棒。
(How to read it?)
（如何读？）
She.
她。
It's a place name,
这是一个地名，
She County.
歙县。
Mr. Zhong, you don't need to learn obscure characters.
钟老师，你不需要 学晦涩难懂的字。
What I've taught you is enough.
我教给你的就足够了。
(I'm already mute,)
（我已经哑了）
(I can't be blind.)
（我不能瞎了。）
If you continue learning,
如果你继续学习，
I won't have enough knowledge to teach you.
我没有足够的知识 来教你。
You will have to go to school with me.
你必须和我一起去学校。
(I won't go.)
（我不会去。）
(I'm afraid the teacher will beat me.)
（我怕老师会打我。）
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
Speaking of the teacher beating students,
说到老师 打学生，
I think I know
我想我知道
whose skull is buried in Mr. Wang's yard.
他的头骨埋 在王先生的院子里。
Where are you going?
你要去哪里？
To a cemetery.
到一个墓地。
Why would you visit it?
你为什么要参观它？
Today is the death day of a friend of mine.
今天是我一个朋友的忌日。
I'm going to visit him.
我要去拜访他。
Do you have friends other than me?
除了我之外你还有朋友吗？
How long have you known me?
你认识我多久了？
Almost a year.
快一年了。
That friend of mine
我的那个朋友
has been dead for five years.
已经去世五年了。
His name is Qiao Gou'er.
His name is Qiao Gou'er.
Charge.
收费。
Qiao Gou'er, follow me.
Qiao Gou'er, follow me.
Go.
去。
Charge.
收费。
Adviser?
顾问？
Yes.
是的。
How should I deal with this turtle?
我该怎么对付这只乌龟呢？
Turtles don't need hands or feet to turn over.
海龟不需要手 或脚来翻身。
A nudge with the head can make them flip over.
用头轻轻一推 就能让它们翻过来。
Roll over.
滚下。
You should have stayed away from them.
你应该远离他们。
We were originally familiar with each other.
我们原本就很熟悉 。
But later,
但后来，
a kid's mother told him
一个孩子的妈妈告诉他
that I was a turtle
我是一只乌龟
and told him not to play with me.
并告诉他不要和我玩。
After that, when they saw me,
之后，当他们看到我时，
they started calling me turtle
他们开始叫我乌龟
and bullying me.
还欺负我。
That is true for people.
对人来说也是如此。
Is Qiao Gou'er really your friend?
乔狗儿真的是你的朋友吗？
Not at this moment.
不是现在。
I want to see a turtle swimming.
我想看乌龟游泳。
- One.
- 一。
Two.
二。
- Two.
- 二。
- Three.
- 三。
A turtle is swimming.
一只乌龟正在游泳。
Not all turtles can swim.
并不是所有的乌龟都会游泳。
Did the turtle drown?
乌龟淹死了吗？
The turtle dived and escaped.
乌龟潜入水中逃脱了。
Let's go.
我们走吧。
Turtle.
龟。
Wake up.
醒来。
Where are the other people?
其他人在哪里？
They have left.
他们已经离开了。
They threw me into the river.
他们把我扔进河里。
I saw it.
我看到了。
If I hadn't,
如果我没有的话
you...
你...
You would have drowned.
你会被淹死的。
I couldn't just stand by and watch you die.
我不能袖手旁观 ，看着你死去。
Thank you.
谢谢。
It's okay.
没关系。
Turns out you are
原来你是
a useless turtle.
一只无用的乌龟。
You can't even swim.
你甚至不会游泳。
Perhaps, it's because I am a turtle from the Cuihua Tower.
或许，因为我是翠华楼的乌龟吧。
There are many turtles in the Cuihua Tower.
翠华楼里有很多乌龟。
Yet, none of them can swim.
然而，他们都不会游泳。
Now I can swim.
现在我会游泳了。
Qiao Gou'er taught me.
Qiao Gou'er taught me.
Qiao Gou'er, I have a favor to ask you.
乔狗儿，我有件事想拜托你。
Can you ask them
你可以问他们吗
to stop bullying me?
停止欺负我？
Okay.
好的。
Since I went to the school,
自从我去学校之后，
I've been distant from them.
我和他们已经疏远了。
But I'm sure they don't dare to disobey me.
但我确信 他们不敢违抗我。
You go to school?
你去上学？
Is it fun?
好玩吗？
No, it's not.
不，这不对。
My teacher punishes students.
我的老师惩罚学生。
By the way, what's your surname?
顺便问一下，你姓什么？
Why?
为什么？
I'm studying the Hundred Family Surnames.
我正在研究 百家姓。
I want to know your surname.
我想知道你的姓氏。
I don't have a surname.
我没有姓氏。
My mother didn't know who my father was.
我母亲不知道我父亲是谁。
Was your mother from the Cuihua Tower?
你母亲是翠华楼的吗？
My mother is dead.
我母亲死了。
But she was before she died.
但她在死之前。
My mother is dead too.
我的母亲也死了。
You wait here for me.
你在这里等我。
I will get you some pastries.
我会给你一些糕点。
Don't bother.
别打扰。
I'm leaving.
我走了。
Qiao Gou'er.
Qiao Gou'er.
Thank you for saving my life.
谢谢你救了我的命。
No problem.
没问题。
I'll come to play with you after school tomorrow.
明天放学后我来找你玩 。
Wait for me by the river bank.
在河边等我。
Okay.
好的。
His father has already come.
他的父亲已经来了。
I waited for him as scheduled,
我按照预定的时间等他
but he didn't show up.
但他没有出现。
He was missing for several days.
他已经失踪好几天了。
I went to his family's shop to look for him,
我去他家的店里 找他，
but I didn't see him.
但我没有看到他。
His neighbors said he had gone missing.
他的邻居说他失踪了。
His father closed the shop to look for him everywhere.
他的父亲关掉了商店 ，到处寻找他。
Later,
之后，
someone found a headless child
有人发现了一个无头儿童
behind the stage.
舞台后面。
A headless child?
无头小孩？
It was chopped off.
它被砍掉了。
That was Qiao Gou'er?
那是乔狗儿？
His father recognized him
他的父亲认出了他
from his clothes and the scars on his back.
从他的衣服 和背上的伤疤。
His father once hit him with a wooden spoon.
他的父亲有一次用木勺打他。
The spoon broke,
勺子坏了，
(and the wood chips were left all over his back.)
（他的背上到处都是木屑。）
He showed me his scars.
他给我看了他的伤疤。
Today is his death anniversary.
今天是他的忌日。
So this incident happened in October.
所以这件事发生在十月份。
So, Qiao Gou'er
So, Qiao Gou'er
was not killed at the theater.
没有在剧院被杀。
Why?
为什么？
No holidays or festivals.
没有假期或节日。
Other than the market day,
除了集市日之外，
no theatrical troupes will perform.
没有剧团演出。
And no one will be at the theater.
而且没有人会去剧院。
The murderer dumped the body there
凶手把尸体扔在那里
for this reason.
为此原因。
I have never thought about this.
我从来没有想过这个问题。
Before Qiao Gou'er died,
Before Qiao Gou'er died,
who saw him last?
谁最后见到他？
It should be his classmates.
应该是他的同学。
His classmate left with him after school.
放学后，他的同学 和他一起离开了。
We were supposed to meet and play together.
我们本来应该 见面并一起玩耍。
He said he would teach me to write,
他说要教我写字
and he would bring a pen for me.
他会给我带来一支笔。
Which school was he attending before?
他以前在哪所学校上学？
His teacher was Mr. Wang.
他的老师是王先生。
Wulei School?
五雷学校？
Yes.
是的。
According to the coroner,
据验尸官称，
this is the skull of a teenage child.
这是一个十几岁孩子的头骨。
It's been a long time.
已经很久了。
Look.
看。
His occipital bone is broken.
他的枕骨骨折了。
If it's not broken after death,
如果死后不破的话
this boy should be killed
这个男孩应该被杀
by a heavy blow to the back of the head.
后脑勺受到重击。
Look at his cervical vertebrae.
看看他的颈椎。
There seem to be many marks
貌似有很多痕迹
of being chopped by an ax on the cervical vertebrae.
被 斧子砍在颈椎上。
The murderer must have tried many times
凶手一定尝试过很多次
before he could chop off the head.
在他砍下头之前。
Can this
这个可以吗
be used to arrest and interrogate Mr. Wang?
用来抓捕 、审问王先生？
It's an old case.
这是一个老案例了。
If his family doesn't report,
如果家人不报案
we have no way to start investigating.
我们没有办法开始调查。
So you mean I should tell Qiao Gou'er's father
所以你的意思是 我应该告诉乔狗儿的父亲
about this first?
首先关于这个？
I suggest you better not go.
我建议你最好别去。
Why?
为什么？
Mr. Wang is influential as a scholar.
王先生作为一位颇有影响的学者。
Based on this evidence,
根据这一证据，
you can't charge him.
你不能向他收费。
We can do an autopsy
我们可以进行尸检
to compare the fracture on the spine.
比较脊柱骨折情况。
Even if you can prove
就算你能证明
that this is Qiao Gou'er's skull,
这就是乔狗儿的头骨，
so what?
所以呢？
Mr. Wang can say
王先生可以说
he knows nothing about this
他对此一无所知
and doesn't know who buried this skull in his yard.
也不知道是 谁把这个头骨埋在他的院子里。
I can testify.
我可以作证。
Can you?
你可以吗？
It's useless.
没用的。
Firstly, you're a child.
首先，你是个孩子。
Secondly...
第二...
Secondly, I'm a servant,
其次，我是一个仆人，
a lowly-born kid, right?
出身卑微的孩子吧？
That's why I can't bring down a respected scholar, right?
所以我不能 打倒一位德高望重的学者吧？
Lu Zhi,
Lu Zhi,
when you grow up, you'll understand.
当你长大后， 你就会明白。
Actually...
实际上...
So, someone can easily escape punishment
所以，有人很容易逃脱惩罚
after killing a person?
杀了一个人之后？
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
I am educated.
我受过教育。
I think
我认为
the world is not the same as what's written in the books.
世界和书本上写的不一样。
(What is different?)
（有什么不同吗？）
Books always encourage people to be good.
书籍总是鼓励人们 向善。
But I always feel
但我总觉得
it's hard to be good,
做个好人很难
but easy to do evil.
但容易作恶。
(There are few good and evil people.)
（善恶之人很少。）
Are you saying
你是说
that both extremely good and evil people are rare in this world?
这世间，极善极恶的人都是罕见的吗？
I see.
我懂了。
For me,
为我，
you are a good person.
你是个好人。
So is Mr. Lu.
卢先生也是如此。
Mr. Zhong, Master Lu.
Mr. Zhong, Master Lu.
Mr. Lu is looking for you.
卢先生正在找你。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
I think I understand.
我想我明白。
What's going on?
这是怎么回事？
The two account books are both from the Hongshun Textile Mill.
这两本账本均 来自宏顺纺织厂。
One of them was falsified.
其中一份被伪造了。
I've read two pages.
我读了两页。
It's short of 2,500 taels of silver.
还差2500两白银。
So, what do you think is going on?
那么，您认为发生了什么事？
Mr. Lu, it involves your friends.
卢先生，这涉及到你的朋友们。
I dare not say.
我不敢说。
What's there to be afraid to say?
有什么好害怕说的呢？
Say it.
说吧。
The Hongshun Textile Mill was co-founded by you and Mr. Zhao.
宏顺纺织厂 是您和赵先生共同创办的。
You hold a 60 percent stake.
您持有 60% 的股份。
Mr. Zhao only has 40 percent.
赵先生只有40%。
The manager Tong is appointed by Mr. Zhao.
童经理 由赵先生任命。
The bookkeeper Mr. Li is from out of town,
簿记员李先生是 外地人，
saying he was recommended by someone else,
说是 别人推荐的，
but in fact, you secretly appointed him
但事实上，你暗中任命了他
to keep an eye on the accounts.
密切关注账目。
You often send me on errands.
你经常派我去办事。
I have a good understanding
我有一个很好的理解
of the people at the Hongshun Textile Mill.
宏顺纺织厂的人们。
In my opinion,
在我看来，
the only one who could skim off this much money
唯一一个 能偷走这么多钱的人
would be Mr. Zhao.
就是赵先生。
Mr. Zhao must have forced Mr. Li
一定是赵先生强迫了李先生
not to record it in the accounts.
不要将其记录在账目中。
That's why Mr. Li wrote another account book.
所以李先生 又写了一本账本。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
This kid is really smart.
这孩子真是聪明啊。
I haven't said anything yet,
我还没说什么
and you've guessed it all correctly.
你已经猜对了。
mr. Li.
先生。李。
This isn't the first time that Mr. Zhao
这不是赵先生第一次
has done something like this, right?
做过这样的事吧？
Lu Zhi.
Lu Zhi.
Why?
为什么？
I'm just guessing.
我只是猜测。
Normally, he should start with small amounts.
通常，他应该 从小量开始。
Then, as he gets bolder,
然后，当他胆子越来越大时，
the amounts become larger.
金额变得更大。
I don't think he started
我不认为他开始了
with 2,500 taels of silver.
有白银2500两。
Yes.
是的。
It has been more than a year.
已经一年多了。
He's embezzled
他贪污了
4,300 taels of silver.
银子四千三百两。
Lu Zhi.
Lu Zhi.
What do you think we should do about this?
您认为 我们应该对此做什么？
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
We can't ignore this matter.
我们不能忽视这个问题。
Otherwise, Mr. Zhao will become more brazen.
不然的话，赵先生 会更加肆无忌惮。
Reasonably, we can report this to the authorities.
按理说，我们可以 向当局举报此事。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
If you can bear this,
如果你能承受这个，
you could give Mr. Zhao a warning
你可以给赵先生一个警告
and ask him to return the money.
并要求他归还钱。
If you can't tolerate it,
如果你无法忍受的话
you'll have to end the cooperation with him.
你必须终止 与他的合作。
End the cooperation?
结束合作？
Lu Zhi,
Lu Zhi,
you are still too young
你还太年轻
and lack experience.
并且缺乏经验。
Mr. Zhao
Mr. Zhao
loves pigeons.
喜欢鸽子。
Lu Zhong.
Lu Zhong.
Send my pair of pigeons to him
把我的一对鸽子寄给他
and invite him over for a drink.
并邀请他过来喝一杯。
Tonight.
今晚。
Bring Zhang Gui to show him the way.
带张贵来给他带路。
Mr. Zhao, let me toast you again.
赵先生，我再敬你一杯。
- Master Lu. - Chen Wang.
- Master Lu. - Chen Wang.
Give the liquor to me.
把酒给我。
Mr. Zhao got drunk.
赵先生喝醉了。
He will stay over here.
他会留在这里。
You tell Ms. Li
你告诉李小姐
to tidy up the guest room.
收拾客房。
Okay.
好的。
Zhang Gui.
Zhang Gui.
Master Lu.
卢老师。
I was...
我曾是...
You did an errand for Mr. Lu, right?
你是给陆先生办事的吧？
Yes, you're right.
你是对的。
Did it go well?
进展顺利吗？
Yes. I did it well.
是的。我做得很好。
You've worked hard.
你辛苦了。
By the way,
顺便一提，
some aged liquor was left during the banquet.
宴会中还剩下一些陈酒。
I'm keeping a jar of liquor for myself.
我给自己留了一罐酒。
Once you two have handled your business,
当你们两个处理完你们的事情后
come and find me.
来找我吧。
- Thank you.
- 谢谢。
Mr. Zhao, you've been earning money lately.
赵先生，你 最近赚钱了。
What makes you say that?
是什么让你这么说？
I heard you're doing the moneylending business.
我听说你在做 放债生意。
That's a lucrative business.
这是一项有利可图的生意。
Are you talking about that?
你在说那个吗？
I'm merely working with a partner,
我只是和一个伙伴一起工作，
being a silent money backer.
是一个沉默的资金支持者。
How much interest rate will you get?
您将获得多少利率？
4 li per month.
每月四里。
4 li per month?
一个月4里？
So, for 4,300 taels of silver,
那么，4300两白银，
the monthly interest will be 172 taels of silver. Good.
每月利息 为172两白银。好的。
You'd earn more than from a shop.
你赚的钱比在商店赚的还多。
You're quite good at arithmetic.
你算术相当不错。
But no one borrows that much.
但没有人借那么多钱。
Besides,
除了，
who can give 4,300 taels of silver?
谁能给4300两白银？
I can.
我可以。
Mr. Zhao.
Mr. Zhao.
Didn't you borrow 4,300 taels of silver
你不是借了四千三百两银子吗？
from the Hongshun Textile Mill?
宏顺纺织厂的？
I was wondering
我想知道
why you suddenly treated me yesterday.
为什么你昨天突然对我这样。
Well,
出色地，
is it a trap?
这是一个陷阱吗？
If this cup is broken,
如果这个杯子破了
will I be killed right now?
我现在会被杀吗？
Merely 4,300 taels of silver
仅仅4300两白银
are nothing to me.
对我来说没什么。
You have no relatives in Du County, right?
你在杜县没有亲戚 吧？
Well, my family
嗯，我的家人
has so many relatives here.
这里有很多亲戚。
You can't mean to sue me
你不可能是故意要起诉我
for such a small amount of money.
为了这么点钱。
What a coincidence.
真是巧合啊。
Just the day before yesterday,
就在前天，
the County Magistrate invited me
县长邀请我
to his mansion tomorrow.
明天去他的宅邸。
So, you can
所以你可以
let the County Magistrate arrest me.
让县长逮捕我。
Well...
出色地...
I almost forgot.
我差点忘了。
I have a poor memory.
我的记忆力很差。
I hold the title of Imperial Scholar.
我拥有翰林学士的头衔。
If you intend to bring me down,
如果你想打倒我的话
you're going to work harder.
你会更加努力地工作。
You have to strip my title first.
你得先剥夺我的头衔。
In this case,
在这种情况下，
I'm leaving.
我走了。
Mr. Zhao.
Mr. Zhao.
I was merely joking around.
我只是开个玩笑。
Are you taking it seriously?
你认真对待吗？
Why would I
我为什么要
break off our friendship
断绝我们的友谊
for merely 4,300 taels of silver?
仅仅四千三百两白银？
Mr. Zhao.
Mr. Zhao.
Please sit.
请坐。
You drank too much last night.
你昨晚喝太多了。
You must be feeling uncomfortable.
你一定感觉不舒服。
I've specifically instructed the chef
我特意吩咐了厨师
to make you a hangover soup.
给你做一碗醒酒汤。
This soup
这汤
is made from the wingtips of a chick,
由小鸡的翼尖制成，
finely chopped into shreds.
切成细丝。
Add spices, scallions, cilantro,
加入香料，葱，香菜，
pickled bamboo shoots, soy sauce and so on.
腌笋、 酱油等。
It's stewed into soup.
是炖成汤的。
It's the best for sobering up and warming the stomach.
是醒酒 暖胃的最佳选择。
Come on.
快点。
Mr. Zhao.
Mr. Zhao.
Have a try.
试试。
Consider it as my apology.
就当是我的道歉吧。
How does it taste?
它什么味？
Delicious.
可口的。
I can tell
我可以告诉
you are still angry with me.
你还在生我的气。
You won't even have a bit more of the hangover soup
你连一滴 醒酒汤都不会喝
I specifically made for you.
我专门为你做的。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
Actually, I have been wanting
其实我一直想要
to discuss this matter with you.
来和你讨论这个问题。
I just couldn't find the right time.
我只是找不到合适的时间。
Mr. Zhao, it doesn't matter.
赵先生，没关系。
How about this?
这个怎么样？
Let's drink up this soup.
我们把这汤喝完吧。
After this,
在这之后，
we're over it.
我们已经结束了。
What about it?
那又怎样呢？
Good.
好的。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
This soup
这汤
is indeed delicious.
确实好吃。
By the way, I got caught up in drinking yesterday.
顺便说一句，我 昨天喝酒了。
I forgot to ask you.
我忘了问你。
The other day,
另一天，
they gave me a pair of pigeons.
他们给了我一对鸽子。
They're called Zihexiu
他们叫紫鹤秀
or called Purple Jade.
或称紫玉。
I don't know much about pigeons.
我对鸽子了解不多。
So, I sent my man to deliver them to you.
所以我派了我的人 去把它们交给你。
Do you like them?
你喜欢他们吗？
Yes.
是的。
My man told me about one thing.
我的男人告诉我一件事。
You're raising a pair of valuable pigeons.
你正在饲养一对 珍贵的鸽子。
You breed them
你培育它们
separately.
分别地。
What is its name?
它叫什么名字？
It's called Bronze Wing.
它的名字叫青铜翼。
So why?
所以为什么？
This kind of pigeon
这种鸽子
is snow-white all over
全身雪白
except for a pair
除了一对
of bronze wings.
的青铜翅膀。
Well,
出色地，
the jade bird is inlaid with purple-gold wings,
玉鸟镶嵌 着紫金翅膀，
half-hidden by the translucent white clouds.
半透明的白云遮住了。
The jade bird is inlaid with purple-gold wings.
玉鸟镶嵌 着紫金翅膀。
The hangover soup was made
醒酒汤就做好了
of bronze wings.
的青铜翅膀。
But,
但，
I instructed the cook
我吩咐厨师
to reserve
预留
the feathers.
羽毛。
Look, is this your Bronze Wing?
看看，这是你的青铜翼吗？
Lu Yuanbao.
Lu Yuanbao.
You must be confused.
你一定很困惑。
Before the banquet yesterday,
昨天的宴会之前，
you had kept your pigeons safely
你已经安全地保护了你的鸽子
in your cage.
在你的笼子里。
How did they end up on my dining table?
它们怎么会出现在我的餐桌上？
You were absolutely correct.
你是完全正确的。
I have no power
我没有权力
and no fame.
并且没有名气。
However,
然而，
it's easy for me
这对我来说很容易
to take some living
谋生
or dead object
或死物体
from your house
从你家
without leaving any trace.
不留任何痕迹。
You don't believe it?
你不相信吗？
You can hurry home to have a look.
你可以赶紧回家看看。
Before leaving,
离开之前，
take your pigeons back with you.
把你的鸽子带回来。
Mr. Lu, I'm wrong.
陆先生，我错了。
Don't be mad.
别生气。
I'll repay the money
我会还钱的
within three months.
三个月内。
That's a trivial matter.
这是一件小事。
It can be deducted from your future dividends.
它可以 从您未来的股息中扣除。
But since you insist on this,
但既然你这么坚持，
I can hardly refuse.
我很难拒绝。
Let's sign a note.
我们来签个字吧。
I'll sign it.
我会签的。
mr. Sun.
先生。太阳。
Didn't you say 4,300 taels of silver?
不是说四千三百两银子吗？
How come it's 5,000 now?
怎么现在就5000了？
Mr. Zhao.
Mr. Zhao.
With our relationship,
以我们的关系，
I can't possibly accept the interest
我不可能接受这个兴趣
of 172 taels of silver.
银子172两。
So, I rounded off the principal to a full number.
因此，我将本金四舍五入 为整数。
It's easier to remember.
更容易记住。
You think it's improper?
你觉得不妥吗？
- No. - I can change it.
- 不。 - 我可以改变它。
No, it's fine.
不，还好。
I'll sign it.
我会签的。
Lu Zhi, help Mr. Zhao.
Lu Zhi, help Mr. Zhao.
Well,
出色地，
that jade bird or something?
那个玉鸟什么的？
The jade bird is inlaid with purple-gold wings.
玉鸟镶嵌 着紫金翅膀。
Purple-gold wings
紫金色翅膀
are gone.
消失了。
They're gone.
他们走了。
Zhang Gui.
Zhang Gui.
Good for you.
对你有好处。
You're not only a watchdog.
你不仅仅是一个看门狗。
You also stole pigeons.
你还偷鸽子。
Shiqi.
Shiqi.
Master Lu.
卢老师。
This is my senior Liu Shiqi.
这是我师兄刘士奇。
He's seriously injured and came to me.
他受了重伤，来找我。
I can't ignore him.
我不能忽视他。
But...
但...
You'll be heavily punished
你将受到严厉的惩罚
if Mr. Lu finds out.
如果陆先生知道了。
It's not a big deal to be punished.
受到惩罚也不是什么大事。
What I fear is...
我害怕的是...
Master Lu.
卢老师。
To be honest,
说实话，
my senior is a vagrant.
我的前辈是个无业游民。
He committed many crimes.
他犯下了许多罪行。
I fear Mr. Lu will turn him in.
我担心卢先生会告发他。
But if we don't turn him in,
但如果我们不举报他
we're harboring bandits.
我们窝藏土匪。
My senior
我的前辈
and I are closer than others.
而且我比其他人更亲近。
The two of us
我们俩
were both expelled by our master.
都被我们的主人驱逐了。
I don't want to implicate the Lu family and you.
我不想 连累陆家和你。
I want to ask for advice from you.
我想征求你的意见。
If you think he can hide here,
如果你认为他可以躲在这里
I'll let him stay before recovering.
在康复之前我会让他留下来。
If you think it's inappropriate,
如果你觉得不合适的话
I will take him away now.
我现在就带他走。
Do you have anywhere else to go?
你还有别的地方可去吗？
Right now,
现在，
I have nowhere to go.
我无处可去。
I can't stay in the city.
我不能留在城里。
Zhang Gui.
Zhang Gui.
I appreciate your trust.
我感谢您的信任。
I'll surely think of a solution.
我一定会想办法解决的。
But I have to ask
但我必须问
what exactly
到底是什么
does Mr. Liu do?
刘先生有吗？
Liu Shiqi the Ghost Hand.
Liu Shiqi the Ghost Hand.
Kill anyone in an instant.
瞬间杀掉任何人。
Whoever is doomed
谁都注定了
shall not hide from him.
不会向他隐瞒。
He's paid
他付了钱
to kill for others.
为他人杀人。
I shouldn't have asked.
我不应该问。
Hiding information
隐藏信息
is disloyal to the Lu family.
对陆家不忠。
But if I sold you out,
但如果我出卖了你
I'd be betraying your trust in me.
我会辜负你对我的信任。
Master Lu.
卢老师。
Never mind.
没关系。
Regardless of what he does,
不管他做什么，
I will consider him as your senior.
我会把他视为你的前辈。
Master Lu.
卢老师。
Even if we keep this from Mr. Lu,
就算我们瞒着陆先生
we won't be able to hide it from Mr. Zhong.
我们无法 向钟先生隐瞒。
It's difficult.
它很难。
We can't tell Mr. Zhong right now.
我们现在不能告诉钟先生。
Let me think about it.
让我想想。
By the way,
顺便一提，
the other two guards in your courtyard
你院子里的另外两个守卫
once worked in the Escort Agency.
曾在镖局工作。
They're difficult.
他们很难。
You mean Bao Sheng and Zhao Liang?
You mean Bao Sheng and Zhao Liang?
I will definitely be careful.
我一定会小心的。
Thank you so much, Master Lu.
非常感谢卢老师。
Not at all.
一点也不。
I just ghostwrote a home letter.
我刚刚代笔了一封家信。
See you, Master Lu.
再见，卢老师。
Master Lu, since you're here,
卢老师既然来了，
why don't you stay longer?
你为什么不再多呆一会儿呢？
Zhao Liang, I have errands to run today.
赵亮，我今天还有事要办。
How about tomorrow?
明天怎么样？
Tomorrow, I'll go to the kitchen
明天我去厨房
to get a couple of dishes.
点几道菜。
I'll drink with you and Bao Sheng.
我和你还有宝生一起喝酒。
We should be honored.
我们应该感到荣幸。
Yes.
是的。
If you say that, I won't come.
你要是这么说我就不来了
Master Lu.
卢老师。
We'll be waiting for you tomorrow.
明天我们会等你。
Okay.
好的。
See you tomorrow.
明天见。
Take care, Master Lu.
卢老师保重。
(The three bodyguards are highly paid.)
（这三位保镖的薪水很高。）
(Among them, the most expensive one)
（其中最贵的）
(is Zhang Gui.)
（是张贵。）
(Many martial arts practitioners like to brag about their masters,)
（很多习武之人都喜欢 吹嘘自己的师父，）
(but Zhang Gui never does.)
（但张贵从来不这样做。）
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
(Do you know about this?)
（你知道这件事吗？）
I know.
我知道。
He has been seriously injured.
他受了重伤。
I haven't figured out how to tell you about this yet.
我还没想好 如何告诉你这件事。
(Do you know who he is?)
（你知道他是谁吗？）
I know.
我知道。
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
He is the famous Ghost Hand, Liu Shiqi.
他就是大名鼎鼎的鬼手柳十七。
He is seriously injured now.
他现在受了重伤。
If he could move a little,
如果他能稍微动一下的话
we wouldn't dare to enter this room unarmed.
我们不敢 手无寸铁地进入这个房间。
How dare he hide him in our house.
他竟然敢把他藏在我们家里。
What is Zhang Gui thinking?
张贵在想什么？
Mr. Zhong.
Mr. Zhong.
Calm down, guys.
冷静点，伙计们。
We are all making a living in the Lu family.
我们都是在陆家谋生的。
Yeah, we are paid by Mr. Lu.
是的，我们的工资是卢先生的。
So naturally, we can't harbor
所以我们自然不能隐瞒
a murderer in his house.
他家里有一个凶手。
You're unhappy that my salary is higher than yours.
我的工资比你高，你不高兴。
Sadly, your skills are lower than mine.
可惜你的技术比我低。
If you didn't hold a knife to my senior,
如果你没有拿刀对着我的前辈
how could I let you take me down?
我怎么能让你把我打倒呢？
Shut up.
住口。
Zhang Gui, stop talking!
张贵，别说话了！
There must be a misunderstanding.
一定有误会。
Zhang Gui's senior has been seriously injured.
张贵的师兄 受了重伤。
If it were you two,
如果是你们两个的话
you couldn't just watch him die, right?
你总不能眼睁睁地看着他死吧？
No matter who he is,
不管他是谁，
given his serious injury,
鉴于他的伤势严重，
he could do nothing now.
他现在无能为力。
Please be merciful.
请仁慈。
When he's up and about,
当他起身走动时，
Zhang Gui will send him away.
张贵将他送走。
Master Lu.
卢老师。
After that,
在那之后，
Zhang Gui can be his inside man.
张贵可以成为他的内线。
They can rob money together
他们可以一起抢钱
and kill people in this house.
并杀死这所房子里的人。
Master Lu, we've already tied him up
鲁大师，我们已经把他绑起来了
and can't let him go.
并且不能让他走。
We listen to Mr. Zhong.
我们听钟先生的。
(What do you think?)
（你怎么认为？）
We have to report to Ms. Lu first.
我们得先向卢女士汇报。
Send Zhang Gui and Liu Shiqi to the Yamen.
Send Zhang Gui and Liu Shiqi to the Yamen.
(What about him?)
（那么他呢？）
Master Lu?
鲁大师？
Let Mr. Lu decide.
让陆先生决定吧。
(You two are very loyal.)
（你们两个非常忠诚。）
We're doing our job.
我们正在做我们的工作。
(You watch him.)
（你看着他。）
(No Rush in Penalty)
（不急于判罚）
???In the middle of the bone, and beside the blade???
???在骨头中间， 刀刃旁边???
???There's something sweet and sticky???
???有一些又甜又粘的东西???
???Biting through the old time???
???穿越旧时光???
???Some cry, and some sleep???
???有的哭，有的睡？？？
???Abundant offerings are served for sacrifice???
??? 祭祀的祭品很丰富???
???There are barren mounds, with flies flying around???
???荒丘荒， 苍蝇乱飞???
???Remote ancient road and prosperous city???
???偏远古道 、繁华都市???
???Wild fires never cease, withering and flourishing???
???野火永不停息， 枯萎又繁盛???
???A few columns of smoke are curling up???
???几柱烟雾袅袅升起???
???You make a wish???
???你许个愿吧???
???Empty promises and miserable stories???
???空洞的承诺和悲惨的故事???
???Disappear without trace???
？？？消失得无影无踪？？？
???Abundant offerings are served for sacrifice???
??? 祭祀的祭品很丰富???
???There are barren mounds, with flies flying around???
???荒丘荒， 苍蝇乱飞???
???Remote ancient road and prosperous city???
???偏远古道 、繁华都市???
???Wild fires never cease, withering and flourishing???
???野火永不停息， 枯萎又繁盛???